this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se radio net se radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software for software engineering radio
this is Robert bloomin I have with me
today J crêpes J is the co-founder and
CEO of confluent prior to founding
confluent he was the lead architect for
data infrastructure at LinkedIn J is the
author of a book on event data and
stream processing and it appeared as a
guest on se radio episode 162 project
voldemort J is the author of a LinkedIn
engineering blog post called
the log what every software engineer
should know about real time data is
unifying abstraction and we will be
talking about that blog post today J
welcome back to software engineering
radio thanks so much for having me
anything else you'd like to tell the
listeners before we start the actual
topic no I think that's a great
introduction we're gonna work up to the
idea in your blog post about an
enterprise data integration architecture
organized around log I want to establish
some building blocks first let's talk
about when we have a large enterprise
with many systems if you looked at that
enterprise from 30,000 foot view what
does it look like it usually looks like
a big mess I mean at least you know in
that blog post in a lot of the work
we've done a confluent we usually kind
of draw this spaghetti mess of
interconnection between applications and
data systems with you know ETL processes
that kind of shunt data around in
real-time messaging and point-to-point
kind of RPC communication and and
usually most people look at that big
kind of spaghetti mess and they say yeah
that's right but it's about a thousand
times more complicated than that
in reality you get some idea of sizing
so how many strands of spaghetti and how
many meatballs in a big organization you
talking tens hundreds thousands yeah
you know each each company is different
right but but I think one of the key
points is in some sense if you're
connecting everything to every other
thing then you know if you if you're
gonna have n things you're gonna have
like N squared connections between the
things and that in that kind of fully
connected world and of course no no
organization is fully connected that
they're always striving to towards that
you would always hear oh you know this
needs to be integrated with that and so
on and and you know I think that kind of
scalability problem is maybe at the root
of a lot of the challenges that that
haven't really been solved in the prior
generations of technology in this space
where they were you know they're kind of
helping you integrate thing a with thing
B but you know as you do that and as you
go down this path it's not really
scalable you know across the whole
company when you're talking about I
think a needs to integrate within me
what do you mean by that you know it
could be all kinds of things like you
see all kinds of these kind of data copy
processes where data is getting pulled
out of a relational database and put
into some other relational database or
data store you see integration between
applications you know that could be as
simple as this service calls that
service or you know it could be
something you know more complex than
that you see you know a whole set of
kind of messaging systems that message
queues that send off messages and are
trying to support more complicated
patterns of you know routing and
interconnection you see essentially all
these kind of you know somewhat ad-hoc
data integrations or pipelines and
technology to support it but if you step
back and you look at a company and you
say hey - do we have access to what's
happening in the company in some kind of
standard way that that anything can plug
into usually the answer is you know no
or not really or only partially or it's
it's relatively complicated to get it
what you want you use a term data
integration in your blog post do you
mean something in particular by data
integration that's more specific than
integration in general no I I really
just meant plugging things together you
know how do applications interconnect
how do data systems interconnect you
know I think maybe if I step back the
you know if you think about the his
three of software engineering and
software development and a lot of these
software platforms yeah the problem that
was focused on for for a lot of history
was how to build one application you
know what's the database to support one
application what are the programming
frameworks you know what do we need to
run one app and I think a lot of the
interesting things happening in the
world now or when you kind of zoom out
now people are like hey we we don't have
one application and that application
doesn't exist in a vacuum and it has to
exist as part of a whole kind of
interconnected company like in some
sense we're not building one app in
software we're building like a whole
company in software that needs to
somehow make sense and when something
happens there's many many things that
need to to react like one example I
often give to make this concrete is if
you think about you know a big retailer
you know a lot of people can kind of
understand retail because you understand
stores and buying things and so it's a
it's kind of an intuitive Jemaine and
you think about well you know how many
different systems need to update or
integrate the information if something
sells if they sell a product to a
customer and you know it's clear there's
analytics systems and there's all kinds
of you know coupon and discounted logic
and there's pricing logic and there's a
whole back-end logistics for managing
warehouses and there's you know
reporting systems and there's things
that look for you know fraud and bad
transactions there's all these different
systems that all have to somehow take
into account that something's sold and
update in different ways and so that
that process of kind of taking you know
individual chunks of software and you
know plugging it all together that
that's kind of what I mean by data
integration I don't know if it's a
perfect term I I don't just mean you
know kind of copying data from one place
to the other
is there any way to quantify in terms of
either number of updates or volumes of
data how much data are we talking about
then needs to move around between
applications yeah you know again I think
this this kind of depends on the scale
of the company and then how much of that
company is really kind of modeled in
software and so when you look at a lot
of these big tech companies and you look
at their usage of kafka they actually
have you know billions or hundreds of
billions or even trillions of these
events that are flowing through the
system each
and so that's obvious obviously massive
scale and I think it took years and then
those those companies are more or less
fully modeled in software and if you
look at other companies they're often
not all in software you they have many
things happening in the real world that
have only kind of disconnected
non-integrated you know support in
software and so they might have much
less but if you think about how those
companies would probably exist ten years
from now
I do think companies are getting more
and more to where there's a you know
there's a complete supporting software
infrastructure even for the things
happening in the real world you know
there's there's instrumentation there's
knowledge of that there's support for
that even the things people are doing
there's associated apps and and so on
that helped kind of track it monitor and
that all needs to come together into one
company that that actually works you
know as as an integrated whole before
you went to the solution we'll be
talking about based on invent log you
tried other approaches to integration
and LinkedIn what else was tried and why
did it not work yeah I mean the the
context was and and this post is
actually you know relatively old right
so I think I wrote this you know maybe
at the end of 2013 or beginning of 2014
right around that timeframe and you know
at that time LinkedIn had been through
this journey of kind of rebuilding all
the internal infrastructure for scale
and there wasn't much that was available
off-the-shelf and so when we talked
before it was about a key value store
that we built internally and so we had
all these different data systems and we
were trying to be really smart about the
the use of data and how that would you
know feed back into the applications and
customer experience and you know I felt
like what what we were doing was was
trying to solve that kind of N squared
integration problem of how does this
application trigger off this thing and
how does this data flow into this
analytic system and how do we monitor
this and I feel like we were trying to
solve it you know one one integration at
a time and so we were kind of building a
big team to do that but it was we were
never gonna finish you know we weren't
we weren't even scratching the surface I
think at one point we were like hey what
do we really if we think about what
happens in the business and we try to
say what do we really have coverage for
that you could tap into I think we said
maybe we have about 10 percent of of
everything and we were working very hard
at that point so we're late
okay that so that was the that was the
context and then we thought well you
know what would a solution look like and
it's it's actually not hard to imagine
you say well whatever happens you know
somehow that data that like you know
stream of things that are happening it
should be available and any other system
should be able to tap into it and they
should be able to react or respond or
calculate something or or do something
with it and then and then the you know
the devil is of course in the details so
when you say everything that could be
actually a lot of data and when you say
any system of course the needs of
different systems could be very
different if you have some offline data
warehouse it may read things only once a
day so it may take updates very slowly
if you have you know some kind of very
real-time application that feeds back
into the customer experience it may have
pretty low latency requirements and so
then we were like well you know is this
really possible can you you know can you
you know create something that actually
fulfills all those demands and and do we
need to like our assumption was there
must be something out there in the world
that solved this problem and we were
just you know too dumb like we didn't
know about it and so we we kind of went
through this journey of trying these
different off-the-shelf messaging
systems or our theory was maybe we could
kind of stitch them together in some way
you know and you see this in the
database world well people will take you
know lots of my sequel databases and try
and stitch it together and to some you
know some kind of sharted something
rather and you know we we thought oh
maybe we could do the same thing like
we'll we'll get some of these
off-the-shelf messaging layers and we'll
try and you know stitch it together into
some platform for this and you know it
was it was kind of remarkably
unsuccessful and so then we came back
out and we thought well look you know we
have internal capability to build stuff
from scratch and and we had some ideas
that came out at the database world for
what you really needed to do and that
was kind of what led us to you know
start working on Kafka we'll go more in
depth into that I want to break this
down into stepping stones these bits of
information that are getting shared
let's call them events what is an event
give some examples yeah you know it's
it's one of those things that's so
simple it's almost hard to explain right
so an event is just something that
happens and you know in that reach
example it could be a sale so okay we
sold something to somebody that's an
event the you know the representation of
that and a computer well it could be
some snippet of JSON that says you know
what was sold and where was it sold and
who was it sold to and how much did it
cost and you know the data about what
happened but it's you know obviously the
event isn't really tied to that JSON you
could represent it in some other format
and so so if you think about it it's a
type of data an event is just data and
it's immutable right you know something
that happened it doesn't unhappen and it
happens at a particular point in time
and and so it's just a it's just a fact
actually it's just something that
occurred and you could imagine
representing all kinds of different
things to happen in a business that way
you know I talked about sales but you
know just as easily you could represent
you know some change to some state about
a user so you know LinkedIn maybe
somebody comes in updates their their
user profile you could say okay you know
my profile is now this you know where
this is the the contents of all the
fields that that would be an event like
a profile update event and you you know
in if you if you were making a
ride-sharing app you could say okay you
know my car is currently here right
that's an event it's just this you know
it is true that at this point in time
this car was at this point this position
and it was this driver and you know this
is the ride it was part of and and so on
so so that's all it is it's a very
different way of thinking about data you
know typically we've thought about
databases which are full of you know the
current state of the world right and so
we think about state we think about okay
you know you your database tables it
might have the set of products or the
you know set of customers or whatever
and they you know could get updated but
it's really modeling the current state
of the world and events are about you
know what's happening in the world what
occurred and so that could be something
that's very high-level about the
business that occurred it could be
something very low-level at LinkedIn at
some point they were monitoring even
very low level things like traffic
through network switches and you know so
on as events and you'll see this
actually if you kind of search around in
you know software engineering channels
for events you'll find it's actually
springs up all over the place so in the
world of application monitoring and
observability there's a whole
towards events it's very much about
low-level mechanics of watching you know
software do its job you know if you look
at front-end development there's a whole
movement towards events which is about
capturing what happening and you're
having you eyes that react and respond
and then of course you know in the in
the world of micro services and
applicant you know interaction between
applications there's there's a movement
towards events and so you know it's
actually kind of you know coming out of
the woodwork in all these different
areas and they're all talking about the
same thing events are just things that
happen in the world and you know it's a
very different you know way of thinking
about data but ultimately kind of a very
simple concept once you understand that
you're like oh you know what's the big
deal we may all be conceptually the same
but if you have events which involve
something like a customer bought
something in the old days you'd store
that in your relational database then
other data like monitoring your security
system detected an anomaly maybe these
things are transient low value you don't
want to go to so much expense to capture
them maybe you don't care if you lose
them so are all these events all treated
the same way as if they were all equally
valuable or is there some ability to
tear them based on how much cost you're
willing to incur in relation to the
business value of that class of things
yeah I mean I think I think the first
mental jump is just understanding that
there's such a thing as events and then
we can think about hey how should we
build the right infrastructure for it
you know I think you're a hundred
percent right that it's not like this
concept didn't exist before I think it
just wasn't well supported and so you
would see all these cases where yeah
people are trying to use a relational
database for streams of events and you
know maybe the the most prominent
example of that is for people who know
the world of data warehousing they have
you know such a thing as fact tables and
they have dimension tables and dimension
tables are kind of what you'd expect
it's your you know your set of products
and the set of geographies and so on
that you operate in but the the fact
tables are actually you know the the set
of things that happened you know and
it's always ordered by time and it's
immutable and it's very much like an
event you can't subscribe to it you
can't get it in real time it just gets
done
at the end of the day but but it's kind
of an interesting thing that in order to
analyze a business and try and say okay
what what happened in the business
yesterday you basically have to reinvent
this you know event concept in a
relational database and so so yeah it's
it's nothing new I you know I think the
the new thing we added was you know
concretely what would the data structure
for events be if you if you said hey
this is an important thing you know how
should we represent it in infrastructure
and is it possible to do that in a way
that actually makes it easy to build
around because anybody who's tried to
build you know real time event streams
where you you know you trigger off of it
and process it in real time on top of a
relational databases you know kind of
come to the same conclusion that this is
you're really quite hard you're kind of
you're abusing a piece of infrastructure
that was built for one use case for
something else you know that's that's a
common thing to do but but it just gets
harder and harder and harder to do well
and so so that was kind of our idea was
yeah you know you can't solve all
problems with one piece of
infrastructure but if you take this idea
of events seriously how far can it go
you know what how can you make something
that's really built you know to do that
from from the ground up and if so
hopefully it can go from you know very
low latency to you know kind of long
longer term you know slower storage and
processing and be a basis for you know
all these applications and so on we are
going to get to how that infrastructure
works but one more concept I want to
cover if we're going to integrate many
different events through data and
enterprise do you need a all of the apps
to agree on a common schema for the
events yeah you do you know in a simple
way so you know let's say that I am I'm
trying to you know keep track of all the
sales occurring and there could be many
ways that we sell things like maybe we
sell them online and maybe we sell them
you know in brick-and-mortar stores
right so all of those people it will be
much more convenient if they can all
agree you know this is how we represent
a sale and then we can send it all to
the same event stream and then likewise
for the people who are trying to react
to that or respond or tap into that or
take it and store it somewhere you know
if if they haven't agreed with the
people upstream about what the bytes
mean that they're not going to be able
to make any sense
so they have to agree on what you know
what the representation of a sale is and
then we have to agree like how can it
change over time
you know maybe we'd all love it to be
the case that we just say oh this is
what a sale is it can never change
that's the definition but you know the
reality is we work in businesses that
are evolving all the time and so the
attributes of a sale what can we capture
about a product how can we sell it the
different things that we would record
are going to change as as the users
change and so we have to agree on that
how that can evolve so that things can
you know software upstream can be
updated and software downstream can be
updated but also we don't require the
whole organization to stop and get on to
the new thing with you know some
downtime so there has to be some
agreement around that and so in a sense
it's actually I think more important
than even the schemas in relational
databases because typically a relational
database is a implementation detail of
one application so the application just
kind of needs to agree on the the schema
with itself and even there the schema
can be helpful to make sure that you're
checking constraints on your data and so
on but once you get to multiple
applications all sharing then it becomes
that much more important that we agree
on the structure of data otherwise you
know you could have somebody
broadcasting you know malformed things
out to the the rest of the world that
they can't react to or handle and then
you know casts chaos ensues what are
some of the schema definition formats
are languages that can be used yeah at
least for Kafka we've tried not to
reinvent the wheel there you know there
there's a bunch of these serialization
layers that are common also out in the
world of you know building RPC services
or restful services so you know there's
things like protocol buffers and Avro
and JSON and they all have different
proponents of different kinds you know
for for Kafka and for complement we've
tried to make you know our stuff work
with as many of these as we can we
provide out-of-the-box support for
something called Avro which is kind of a
binary format with a you know JSON
schema that has good support for you
know the evolution of data but but we're
not religious about it people tend to be
the most religious about these you know
kind of formats and standards and our
job is just to build tools that people
work with all of these formats have
common that they are supported by many
different languages and that is probably
essential because every app in and
becoming he's not going to be written in
the same language yeah that that's
that's a really important part of this
as you want to have you know some
definition that's agreed on that that
any you know anybody can plug into and
so you know the kind of things that are
baked into the programming languages
like Java serialization or you know
whatever the the old-school pickling and
Python I mean it's really inappropriate
you know it would work if you were just
sending data to yourself with the same
version of the software doing the
reading and writing but this is
something where you know you're gonna
have many different applications
potentially in the future even in the
present in different languages and those
applications will all change
independently so you can't assume a
single version of everything you can't
assume a single program and they would
you want to have as much independence in
that data as you can we're moving in
these stepping stones toward this
concept of the Kafka event log in your
blog post you introduce the idea of an
event log which is borrowed from the
database world and you're extending it
to the enterprise let's start with how
logs work in single node databases yeah
that's that's a good question so you
know I thought process was we're trying
to solve this problem of when you know
when something happens out in the world
how does it get integrated into all
these different you know systems and
applications so if you know in my retail
example is something is sold and all
these downstream systems need to kind of
react on their their time for him and
you know we were looking for where are
examples where this happens and you know
the the people who are thinking about
this were a set of database engineers
and so one of the ideas that is kind of
under the covers you know it's basically
an implementation detail of databases
but it often leaks out is this concept
of a commit log and that's used to keep
all the different parts of the database
in sync and in a distributed database
it's often used to keep these different
independent nodes in sync and so the
idea is you just take every update that
you want to make and that update yeah
maybe you're saying hey I want to update
my LinkedIn profile to this new value
that that might require changing
multiple things right so that row has
change but different database indexes
may need to update there may be things
that need to you know trigger off of
that if the database supports triggers
all kinds of things may happen in
reaction to that and so the idea is is
very simple these you know commit logs
are really just a file where you just
append you know the change and then the
the you know taking that change in
integrating it into all your data
structures happens only once it's been
committed and so the idea in database is
if you if you want to have some notion
of correctness and consistency and fault
tolerances you know in some sense that
log of committed data that is the
database that's the real truth of what
happened and all the tables and indexes
are just representations that you could
actually recreate off of that log if you
had to write there they're kind of like
a cache of the information that's been
structured for a particular type of
query and so so that's the kind of basic
idea of you know how a commit log is
used it often becomes very important as
an external factor because people often
tap into that commit log so in my sequel
people use the kind of bin log to get
the the sequence of changes out of the
database as well and so it becomes
almost a you know a public API but it's
kind of a an accidental public API I
think in most databases where it's a an
internal detail that ends up getting
exposed and the things that we knew from
database engineering were these commit
logs are the fastest part of the
database so you can write you know a
series of things to disk in a in a
linear order extremely fast and we also
knew from distributed systems that there
was a way to do this at scale across
many nodes that there was you know
consensus protocols and ways of
committing data that would extend beyond
a single machine and and so we thought
that could actually be applied to you
know the enterprise at large you could
actually think about your kind of whole
company instead of data systems and
applications as kind of like one big
data store and you would you know that
you would commit to some log and then it
would be applied elsewhere I formulated
this question in terms of a single node
database and now you've talked about how
it can be generalized to a distributed
system
by which you might say multi-node
Cassandra cluster where every node is
running Cassandra now it sounds like the
next step was you generalize that a
little bit further to the enterprise
where you have these heterogeneous
systems but you're still thinking about
the log in the same way as if the entire
enterprise is one big database did I get
that right
yeah I think that's exactly right so in
traditional single node database the log
is usually just you know on the the file
system and then it would be used to keep
replicas of that database in sync so
they would just take each change that
was applied on the you know primary or
master node and they would apply it on
the kind of secondary follower nodes and
then other applications might sink off
that so you know that was the kind of
typical architecture of a single node
database and then in distributed
databases people came up with you know
techniques for maintaining this kuiper
this type of distributed log across
multiple machines and and this is
figured pretty prominently in a lot of
the architectures of distributed
databases so things like Amazon's Aurora
Yahoo early on had a paper on a system
called key nuts that worked this way I
mean that was the name in the paper
anyway and so it clearly generalizes to
a distributed system where the you know
the individual nodes in that distributed
database all work asynchronously you
know they don't all work in lockstep and
and so it wasn't a huge jump for us to
think about like well what if those
nodes are doing different things with
the event you know that would work as
well two very important properties of
these logs which you've mentioned and
I'd like you to expand on why are these
properties important they are immutable
and append-only you know there's even a
third property which is you know kind of
maybe obvious just from my description
which is they're ordered and I think you
actually need all those things so you
need it to be the case that when
something happens you know new things
can happen but that past history doesn't
change in sneaky ways out from under you
and that's that's really important in a
database the database needs to be able
to take each of these changes integrate
it into its tables if you know there's a
random chain
just happening in the past of history
where you're kind of rewriting history
it's very hard to integrate that in a
correct way especially if you imagine
the database crashing at some instant in
time like what what state are we really
in you know or have we even made a full
atomic change and so you know this idea
really originally came out of the idea
of how do we get you know atomicity and
and how do we have transactional commits
and how do we you know how do we handle
correctness in a database but it's
actually you know arguably even more
important when you get into a big
diverse organization where you have
different parts of the organization you
know have different teams that you know
talk to each other less than they should
and our building independently you know
it needs to be the case that when
something occurs that there's a really
principled way that that propagates out
to all the other systems in the
organization we're at this point we
started talking about the problem of
integration the complexity of
point-to-point integrations you simplify
that you put the log at the center of
the architecture I think we have all the
pieces now or you could answer the
question what does the enterprise
architecture that you're talking about
look like yeah well the idea is that
it's based around events and that you
can think of you know events
representing both the the kind of
activity of the company but also the
state changes so if I update my profile
that's an event and so you could really
think about kind of all the different
types of data in an enterprise those
events and then the question is well
what's the what's the data structure for
an event what's the abstraction that you
know you can give to a software engineer
that they can work off of that and we we
felt this kind of commit log was really
the right way to do that and so the idea
is that you you know you commit to some
kind of log and you say okay this
occurred and this occurred and this
occurred in can many people writing to
that log and then you can have all all
these independent readers who read off
that log and apply the change and they
can do that kind of on their own
timetable so slower systems can do it
slowly real-time systems can do it you
know as quickly as they can and they'll
all get the same sequence of things
they'll all get them in the same order
and they can get them kind of on the
timeframe that they want but but there
has to be strong guarantees around this
right
if data can somehow be lost or oh if a
system goes down for a small period of
time it can't be that data you know
you're missing updates and all the
everything gets out of sync and you have
to go do some you know scavenger hunt to
figure out what happened to your data it
has to be you know guaranteed that when
something happens it will propagate out
to everything that's downstream and we
felt like that you know that that was
actually really clarifying if you kind
of steps back and you just thought this
way you think okay look the things that
happen in a company are events and we
need infrastructure that allows us to
propagate events that kind of a you know
global companies scale then and if we
think hey the the way you would build
that is this kind of commit log then it
really is just this just you know
distributed systems problem of how can
we build that how can we make it
accessible and then how you know what
are the programming abstractions to make
that really easy which is a lot of what
we've done you know since that blog post
was written was really and a confluence
really focused on the kind of up the
stack tools that allow you know people
to build against this in a really simple
way we did on entire show on Kafka it
was 215 it was about four years ago
listeners who want to get some
introduction to it could listen to that
show so I don't want to do a whole basic
intro to coffee here but how is the
Kafka platform changed in the last four
to five years since we lost covered it
yeah it's it's changed in a couple ways
so that the evolution of this was you
know we had a pretty big vision around
you know events and commit logs and how
it could really be kind of the central
nervous system for a company but we
couldn't build it all at once and so the
you know the first version that we built
was very scalable but it didn't provide
you know kind of replicated
fault-tolerance guarantees like a
database would right and so it was
applicable for these kind of high volume
activity data like messaging systems
might have but it wasn't really
applicable for kind of you know core
payments transactions can't lose data
and then you know then we did work to
add replication to that so then we had
something really right about right
around the time that that blog post was
written that was both fault-tolerant and
scalable but it was still relatively
low-level we were giving you this kind
of commit
you could go do with it as you please so
it was kind of a you know a very
primitive abstraction powerful but it
was up to you to figure out how to use
it and of course that's that's a lot of
work to take advantage of so a lot of
Silicon Valley companies it just had
very large engineering teams would you
know build around Kafka just build it
into all their different you know
applications and data systems and they
would get to really large-scale with it
but you know kind of outside of that
world it was very hard for people to
kind of take advantage of the idea and
so then you know I compliment the the
you know kind of big investments we've
made is you know kind of continuing to
make that foundation better and better
but also adding a layer that would
manage kind of pre-built off-the-shelf
connectors so you could just plug in you
know databases if you have my sequel
there's no reason you should have to
build the you know 10,000 and first my
sequel integration you should just be
able to get the connector and use it and
then build stream processing
capabilities it would allow you to build
applications that react to these event
streams and so we we found that people
were just kind of building the same
stuff over and over again as they were
trying to you know work against this and
we realized that in some sense you know
if you think about this kind of commit
log or event stream that you know with
the that that's a foundational
abstraction but it's pretty low level so
it's kind of like you know building
directly on top of that can be a little
bit like building a an application
directly on top of the file system in
terms of its data access and you know a
lot of the work in recent years has been
moving up the stack and trying to make
that more approachable and try and give
you know a much more like a kind of
almost like a relational database way of
working with event streams and that's
been this area of stream processing and
things like Kay sequel that allow you to
just apply sequel on top of data streams
and materialize new data structures and
data formats and things that you can act
upon well put some links in the show
notes where people can read about some
of these features join hundreds of
senior developers engineers and software
architects in New York this February to
learn new skills and technologies at the
o'reilly software architecture
conference network with and learn from
experts as they share their knowledge on
micro services cloud computing and
server lists as well as emerging trends
in a i'm
learning and data analytics whether
you're a seasoned architect or aspiring
to become one the O'Reilly software
architecture conference is designed to
help you go next level save 20% on your
pass with code ser 20 register at
O'Reilly si con comm / se radio one
other area on explore is if you're now
putting this if you're making the event
log the real core of your architecture
where it's becoming the system of record
in order to adopt it you need to ensure
that it has the same degree of disaster
recovery and survivability as the
enterprise database used to be which
some of it means features built into the
system like the ability to create
backups while it's running but then
other investments you need to make
outside of the event log which is what
you do with the backups where do you put
them how often do you have good
operational procedures around recovering
them have kafka evolved a feature set
that makes it worthy of being a system
of record yeah it's gotten better and
better in that area I I think what you
say is exactly right there's a there's a
set of features and then also a set of
operational practices that are that are
really important for anything that's
kind of a critical data store and so
it's important for people who are
adopting Kafka to know you know are they
using it just for transient data or are
they using it as something you can kind
of fall back on or rely upon and if the
latter then definitely the you know the
degree of operational excellence has to
be a lot higher and so it has gotten you
know better and better at storing data
better at scaling the number of
partitions backing up something like a
log is actually really easy because you
can just subscribe to it and copy it
elsewhere so in fact the backup features
and databases are always built on top of
the the commit log and the database or
typically are so that parts you know
relatively relatively straightforward to
do but but that is a critical thing for
people who are trying to you know rely
on this you know commit log as something
that you can actually restore off of
without going back to source systems of
you know
trying to reconstruct it there's some
interesting possibilities with this
architecture I would like to get into
one would be if we have all our data in
let's say a relational database and we
realize there's this new type of
database called a graph database it's a
really good fit to our use case how do
we incorporate these other types of
databases into the enterprise yeah
that's that's a great point that you
raise so one of the nice things about
Kafka is it's kind of independent of any
of the different representations or
query capabilities you might have for
data and so if you have data feeds that
are in Kafka you can easily load them
into different databases and get kind of
almost like a materialized view of that
data and so you can think of you know
data warehousing and analytics layers
that way you could think of a Search
Search index that way you could think of
a graph data store that way and and this
is one of the core use cases people
adopt something like Kafka for they
typically have some kind of relational
database which is serving you know live
user experience type UI and that's
actually creating the the kind of core
transactional data stream so maybe your
your set of users but then there's other
systems like search or analytics that
that need a representation of that data
and so Kafka kind of acts as this you
know log of those changes that can feed
out to all the systems so oftentimes the
data warehouse would feed slow or some
kind of real-time analytics layer might
be faster a search index usually you
want to be in sync you know if it's if
it's meant to be a live kind of search
experience something like a graph
database that's providing different
types of queries could feed off of that
as well and you know that's that's
definitely a core motivation for this
architectures actually as the set of
databases but also even you know in the
cloud a lot of the different SAS
services and so on that you could kind
of tap into data as a set of things has
grown you know the the desire to have
some kind of consistent way of
broadcasting that out gets you know more
and more and we're seeing more of that
where it's you know it's not just new
databases like people have integrations
with things like Salesforce and you know
with with rest services and with all
kinds of other things that they want to
react
something happens in the article you
express the idea that all of these
different types of databases are just
specialized indexes on the event log
what do you mean by that yeah what I
what I mean is you know in some sense if
you peer inside of a lot of the
distributed databases they are kind of a
you know distributed log and then you
know some kind of materialization of the
data that's there for serving queries
and by having this log as a service and
sewn right you can run lots of those
systems in the way we we just described
and you can you could actually compute
new things off the data stream and so
you know it may be the thing that you
want in your search index isn't just the
simple record that you had in the
database it may actually involve
stitching together lots of bits of
information that you have about the
customer and then indexing that and so
you may want to do processing on on top
of that data stream and so you know that
that's very much the idea and then you
can think of that you know that search
cluster is you know it's effectively
just a kind of materialized view of your
data you know it's just a representation
that's feeding off of that commit log in
database terms you could think of it as
a you know in databases they have tables
and they have you know materialized
views that are calculated off the table
so you could think of it very much like
that it's just that this happens to be
in a separate system that last point I
want to drill a little bit down into
this up to now we've been talking about
a lot of examples of an event is some
new information that came into the
system from the outside world like
somebody customer bought something you
could have stock price feeds coming in
from the market a vendor updated their
inventory he's one of your systems to
give that information into your
enterprise but now you're talking about
you could have events that subscribed to
your eternal event stream process the
events and let's say classify this
customer is now a higher tier of
customer or something you information
been able to extract from data that came
in by processing and then you publish
that back out onto the event log in now
other systems can react to that yeah
that's that's exactly right so like a
really simple example is in you know
virtually any big company you have
a bunch of bits of information about
your customers right so you have maybe
some primary account record but you have
interactions with customer service and
you have you know four settings and so
on and you you know your payment
information and so usually one project
that's really common in companies is you
know creating some kind of unified view
of that that's used in a lot of
different applications that's may be
used for analytics and so you can think
of it as really just you need to perform
a kind of continuous join across you
know these different systems which have
different databases and data stores and
so how you know how can you do that how
can you do a kind of continuous join
across you know a bunch of different
systems that aren't even using the same
underlying data storage and you know I
think one answer to that is yeah you
treat the updates in each of those
systems as a kind of stream of events
you use stream processing to you know
join that together and create this
stream of kind of unified customer
profiles and then that could be
materialized in a key-value store it
could be sent off to a data warehouse
for analytics but that that feed is
basically published back as you say as a
log and its own right which is
consumable and subscribable I want to
get into a little bit more of the
programming aspects so application needs
to get into data into the event log how
does it do that yeah there's there's two
ways in Kafka right you can you know
directly write a record and you know
it's actually not hard you just say
something like send and you provide a
kind of key value pair and that's sent
off to some topic that you would specify
and it's appended to the commit log for
that topic and that's kind of like the
lowest level of interaction is you know
it's almost like just saying write in a
file system you just write something and
so that's kind of a push mechanism now
if you think about existing systems you
may have some you know SAS service you
use you may have a database those
systems don't know about Kafka and so
they're not actively going to push data
into Kafka you may actually want to pull
data out of those systems and push it
into Kafka and that's where these
connectors come in and Kafka supports
something called Kafka connects which is
this distributed framework for running
these connector
managing them and so that's the other
that's the other way to get data in and
and then you know of course the you know
the other the final you know version of
that is kind of what you described which
is you may be taking some of these
streams and actually doing something
with it and publishing back some you
know derived stream of data back into
Kafka and using simple application
software using one of these stream
processing tools like Kay sequel and you
know maybe that's a third way all of
these are built on the underlying you
know producer and consumer layers and
Kafka which do the the reads and writes
I was writing an app today I know my
Enterprise has kafka so there's not this
question how do I retrofit this app
that's writing into Postgres so and I
want to make life easy for the
programmer every time I do a transaction
so this app is has its own database as
well let's say that's also postcards
every time I write a transaction two
postcards do I have to now include some
logic to write Kafka or is there a way a
kind of an aspect oriented style where I
could create a cross-cutting concern
against every database transaction that
wouldn't say to ship them all off to
Kafka yeah usually this simple there's
many ways to handle this and some of the
things that some of the events that come
out of applications may have no
representation and a database and you
may just write them directly but but
often the simplest way to do this is to
use the connector infrastructure so most
databases like Postgres they actually
expose the commit log in some way and so
either by you know querying the tables
or reading that commit log you can
actually take that and publish it out in
Chicago's you know data streams for each
of the tables say and and so that's
that's the pattern that's probably most
common and and then there may be
additional cleanup you want to do on
that data and that can often happen you
know via stream processing where you
take the kind of original thing that was
in the database and you stitch it
together into something that is really
what you want to publish out to the
organization that that's in the right
format for consumption I've done all my
domain modeling I understand my business
apps
tractions then we get the database
people involved and they normalize
everything into all these tiny little
tables so I commit this one object it
writes rows into six different tables
now you're gonna look at the commit log
with your connector do you have to
reverse engineer that back or maybe not
reverse engineer that but do almost the
inverse operation to transform that back
into your event log model yeah I mean I
guess there's different patterns for
doing this and it depends somewhat what
your goals are if you need to have read
after write consistency in the database
you do typically want to kind of commit
to that database first and then have the
Kafka log sync off of that and you know
that could mean either you know having a
table that directly represents the event
as well as the you know the the more
normalized representation and the
database or it could mean stitching it
back together off of the normalized
representation and you know that
probably depends whether you're writing
the application from scratch or you're
retrofitting something that already
exists which of those what you would do
if on the other hand that the database
doesn't have to you know have that kind
of read after write consistency you can
always just you know publish the event
stream to Kafka and populate the
database off of that in that first
pattern you talked about then if I
understand it it's more like a double
write but the writes all go to the
database to take advantage of the acid
property of postcards where you'd have
one table and let's say it's called
Kafka log and you write something there
then Kafka could come and pull that out
but you don't have the problem of
updating two different logs and trying
to ensure they both get committed yeah
it depends a bit what you mean by double
right I mean we don't we don't usually
advocate that people kind of you know
write to one and then write to the other
because you know obviously if your
application fails in the middle then you
know the question is how do you keep
those instincts so it's usually better
to write to the database and have Kafka
subscribes to the database or write to
Kafka and have the database subscribe to
that if you don't care about correctness
and of course you can try and do that
double right but it's it's a bit like
those you know keeping caches in sync
that way word it never it never quite
works in the presence of failure and
mult
machines and and so on so usually
picking either the database or Kafka and
having you know one of those to be in
front is is a is a cleaner pattern you
put a table in postcards called Kafka
events and you write to all your
normalized tables and then you write the
event out to that table and that's all
one commits in Postgres and then Kafka
can just look at that one table that's
right and that would that would simplify
the the downstream cleanup you would
need to do and you know that obviously
works only if you're able to go in and
change the application if it's something
owned by somebody else and you just want
to you know subscribe to what's in the
database then you got to stitch it back
together in the stream processing side
which has gotten easier and easier as
the the stream processing tool set has
gotten better so one more main area and
like cover we're getting close to the
end of our time with these event logs
being immutable how do you deal with if
bad events get written to the event log
which could either be human error or you
have some rogue application that has a
bug and it's writing a bunch of bad
events and now they're immutable are you
stuck yeah that's that's a great
question so you know it is very hard if
you have systems all reading off this in
real time to handle kind of bad data you
know it's very similar to a you know the
situation with the database except you
may have many apps that all feed off the
same thing and so as much as possible
you know it is good to actually enforce
these schemas so similar to a database
right you know if you ship a version of
your application that publishes corrupt
data and overwrites good data with it
you're in a bit of a bind you're gonna
have to go kind of rewind and you know
manually truncate and figure out how to
get back into a clean state it's similar
with Kafka where yeah you can kind of
rewind to when it happened but you're
actually better off trying to enforce
the schema correctly and making sure
that valid data is you know is what is
published and that kind of schema
enforcement ends up being really
important as this scales in an
organization I mean we've worked with a
bunch of companies that have done this
and the ones that have taken kind of a
best-effort approach it tends to work up
it to a certain point and then you know
there's just somebody breaking
everything down
all the time because there's so many
readers and so many writers that at any
given point somebody has a has a bug
somewhere what about the schema is
correct but the values are not correct
it has to be somehow cleaned up expose
how do you fix it it's similar to any
contract you might have right so you
have the same issue if you're trying to
you know update individual micro
services and a micro service
architecture if you have no contract at
all that can be very hard even if you
have a contract the contract can't
really cover everything right so you may
say there's some field which is URL
fully normalized fully qualified URL or
is it just the base of the URL right
like ultimately the person upstream and
the person downstream has to agree on
that and and kind of keep that in sync
if if you get something that's wrong you
do have to you know either update the
processing logic to handle that or go go
back and clean out the log which is
going to be a very kind of manual step
that's hard to do it covers the prepared
material I have is there anything else
on this theme or from the article or
discussing that you wanted to cover that
we haven't talked about yeah I think
maybe one of the interesting things that
we've done recently that's very closely
aligned to that is is around case equal
DB which really kind of ties together
the ideas you know we talked about some
of the integration stuff but there was
really kind of three points like
integration stream processing and the
role in data systems and in some sense
that ties together all three so I think
it might be fun to talk about that a
little bit yeah let's go ahead why don't
you describe what what it does what
problem it solves yeah so really just
last week we actually did a release of
case equal DB and this is kind of the
evolution of a system called K sequel
that we've built to allow stream
processing in sequel on top of Kafka and
so the idea was you know these event
streams are new and you know people may
not know how to use them but everybody
knows sequel is if you could just use
sequel on top of the event stream so if
you could say hey you know take the
stream of updates to user profiles and
join that on to the stream of activity
from users and get you know both
together and be able to you know
act on that or transform it all in
sequel that that would be really cool
and we've evolved that system and it's
really actually I think quite exciting
and if you've if you've read this log
article it's even more exciting because
it brings together the ideas about
stream processing you know acting on
real-time streams of events it brings
together the ideas on data systems that
are built around blogs because it turns
out that you know if we want to join our
customer profiles to the customer
activity you need some kind of stored
fault-tolerant representation of
customer profiles and so what this
system now allows you to do that's
pretty cool is you can take these event
streams you can materialize some data
set off of that you can use that data
set to combine with other event streams
and you can query it and so it's it's
it's very much kind of a database built
for working with event stream so you
know it's not meant to replace post
grass or Oracle or whatever you would
you know kind of have as the you know
the backend for a crud application but
it is meant to solve this problem of hey
I want to take a bunch of these
different data streams I want to
materialize it into some data set and
build an application around that aims to
make that as simple as possible and so
it includes both you know sequel for
processing streams of data continuously
as well as the ability to do lookups off
of whatever the result is one if that
solves the problem we've been talking
about where I based on postgrads
I'm gonna commit everything to postcards
and then we have the problem of pulling
it back out on the back end so say I
want it to be in the log why don't I
just write it to the log in the first
place the only problem then is you don't
have the ability to read it from a
sequel like interface until a little bit
of time is elapsed where it propagates
down and gets picked up and added to
sequel as a subscribe step so can I then
put it in stream and if I need to read
it I can query it from sequel out of the
stream now and avoid that consistency
delay yeah I mean the use case that
we're targeting initially it's not quite
that right so our theory was people
aren't going to replace Postgres for
their you
kind of crud applications or arrest
services and you know we're not trying
to get them to do that but if you think
about the applications downstream of
that of actually using event streams
those are actually relatively difficult
to build and they end up being kind of
you're gluing together some of these
connectors and you're gluing together
some stream processing that you know
does something with the events and then
you're eventually gluing on some you
know kind of data store to serve results
up to some application we thought if we
could consolidate the set of things
downstream that would really make life
much simpler and working with the bent
streams and so you know a very simple
example of that that I described was you
know that that kind of customer 360
where you're joining together data feeds
about your customer across seven systems
and then you want to be able to look up
hey what's the current you know what's
the current unified profile for this for
customer one two three and so you could
do that basically just in a couple of
queries and I think that kind of
materialized derived cache I think
that's a problem we see everywhere like
people have these older applications you
know they're running the business you
have new requirements and you need to
build a new set data set that cuts
across some of these the ability to tap
into those and you know create a new
data set off of it and then issue
queries against it to kind of
continually materialize a cached view of
some part of the business that that's
actually really really common and we
think really well-suited to this and
it's much easier to do it in a correct
way than if you're trying to you know do
some dual rights strategy that cuts
across multiple applications in some you
know transient cache because this is
directly fed off of the changelog of all
of those systems so those event streams
populated it's always kept in sync I see
what I think you're saying now is
instead of writing a application to do
that which is high programming
complexity you've reduced it to I can
write a sequel query against Kafka and
get the answer yeah yeah so that what
the the support that this provides is
the ability to manage these connectors
so so in my example the first thing I
need to do is actually capture the
stream from a number of different
databases and so maybe I would you know
I now have sequel support to kind of
declare there's almost like external
tables or external streams and capture
that into Kafka the next thing I need to
do is maybe join and clean up those data
feeds and create my unified customer
profile can do that also with this kind
of stream processing sequel and then the
final thing I need to do is be able to
actually query and say oh I need the
profile for this customer because I need
to put it in my UI and so I could
actually issue those real-time queries
against that that date of heating so so
bringing those together the ability to
you know if you think about it in ETL
terms you're kind of extracting streams
of data you're transforming them and
you're kind of loading them into some
you know stored representation and then
you're actually doing live queries
against them you know it's really that
whole end-to-end stack that would have
otherwise required you know you to glue
together specialized systems for each
part and once you have all the data and
Kafka that becomes the obvious place to
do at least some of this processing yeah
that's exactly right so you know we felt
like the investments with the connectors
helped unlock and get a lot of data into
Kafka and then you know the complaint
people have is great I have all these
ideas for what I could do off of these
streams of events but it's you know in
the end it's pretty hard right you have
to build you know custom Java code or
Python code or whatever that that does
any of these applications it gets
complicated as you think about fault
tolerance and so on and so having data
layer that allows you to do that
declaratively in sequel that handles the
kind of more complex operations like
joining or counting or adding
aggregating that's actually really
valuable that wraps things up J where
can people find you on the internet
probably the easiest way is on Twitter
I'm Jake reps first name last name all
altogether and you know other than that
I you know I've got LinkedIn profiles
and dozen other social media thinks
usually pretty easy to find and
confluent organ people find that
confluence is confluence IO
and so confluent produces you know a
whole platform around Kafka that is you
know community license you can just go
take it and use it we produce also an
enterprise software product that you can
go if you're going to run this in
production we produce a cloud service so
you can actually
you know if you're looking at this Kafka
stuff and you're like I just don't want
to run one more thing you can get it as
a service in you know any of the major
public clouds Google or AWS or your and
you kind of just pay for what you use
and you get all this infrastructure you
know has a service jake reps thank you
very much for speaking to software
engineering radio thanks so much for
having me for software engineering radio
this has been Robert blumen thank you
for listening thanks for listening to se
radio an educational program brought to
you by Triple E software magazine for
more about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of SU radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening
[Music]